Welcome back!
Today we're revising two systems that work as a team: the respiratory system and the circul
atory system.
We'll follow oxygen all the way from the air you breathe to the muscles in your legs,
and learn the exact phrases that score marks.
First, what each system is for.
The respiratory system lets us breathe: it takes in oxygen and removes carbon dioxide.
The circulatory system transports oxygen and digested food to all parts of the body,
and carries wastes away. Now, an important trap.
Breathing means taking air in and pushing air out — a physical action.
Respiration means releasing energy from digested food, using oxygen, inside every cell.
They are not the same! We breathe to supply the oxygen needed for respiration.
Let's follow the path air takes: nose, then windpipe, then lungs,
and finally the air sacs.
At the nose, hairs and mucus trap dust and germs,
and the nose also warms and moistens the air.
The windpipe, or trachea, is a tube that carries air from the nose down to the lungs.
The lungs are the two organs where gaseous exchange takes place.
And inside them are the air sacs,
where oxygen enters the blood and carbon dioxide leaves it.
When we breathe in, air with more oxygen enters, and the chest expands.
When we breathe out, air with more carbon dioxide leaves, and the chest contracts.
Now here's a trap that catches many pupils: inhaled air is not pure oxygen,
and exhaled air is not pure carbon dioxide.
Inhaled air has more oxygen and less carbon dioxide.
Exhaled air has less oxygen and more carbon dioxide.
Both gases are always present — only the amounts change.
Here's the key idea of the whole topic: gaseous exchange.
Memorise this: oxygen from the air in the air sacs passes into the blood.
At the same time, carbon dioxide from the blood passes into the air sacs,
and is breathed out. And why are the air sacs so good at this?
Because there are millions of them, giving a large surface area,
so gaseous exchange can happen quickly.
Now the circulatory system. The heart is a pump, made of muscle.
It pumps blood to all parts of the body, without stopping.
When the heart beats, we can feel a pulse.
And here's the trap: the heart does not make blood, and it does not make oxygen.
Its job is to pump the blood, so that the blood can transport oxygen and digested food.
So what does the blood carry?
Oxygen, picked up at the lungs, and delivered to all body parts.
Digested food, picked up at the small intestine, and delivered to all body parts.
And carbon dioxide, picked up at the body parts,
and delivered back to the lungs to be breathed out.
The blood flows through tiny tubes called blood vessels,
which reach every part of the body, so every cell can receive oxygen and food,
and give up its wastes.
Now let's put the systems together — this is very important for the PSLE.
One: we breathe in, and oxygen enters the air sacs in the lungs.
Two: the oxygen passes into the blood, by gaseous exchange.
Three: the heart pumps the blood, transporting the oxygen,
and digested food from the small intestine, to all parts of the body.
Four: the body cells use the oxygen and food to release energy. That's respiration.
Five: this produces carbon dioxide, which passes into the blood.
And six: the blood carries it back to the lungs, and we breathe it out.
So why do we pant when we run?
Because the muscles are working harder, they need more oxygen to release more energy.
So we breathe faster and deeper, to take in more oxygen and remove more carbon dioxide.
And the heart beats faster, to pump the oxygen-carrying blood to the muscles more quickly.
Always link it back: more oxygen, to the muscles, to release more energy.
Answering technique for Section B. Use these keywords: gaseous exchange. Air sacs.
Large surface area. Oxygen passes into the blood. The heart pumps blood.
Transports, or carries. Digested food from the small intestine. To all parts of the body.
And, release energy.
Then use the system-link formula: oxygen enters the blood at the air sacs.
The heart pumps the blood, which transports the oxygen to all parts of the body,
where it is used to release energy.
Time to test yourself!
Explain how oxygen in the air we breathe reaches the muscles in our legs.
Pause the video and try. Ready?
Here's the model answer: oxygen enters the air sacs in the lungs and passes into the blood.
The heart pumps the blood, which transports the oxygen through the blood vessels to the mus
cles in the legs.
Let's recap. The respiratory system takes in oxygen and removes carbon dioxide.
The air path is nose, windpipe, lungs, air sacs — and the nose traps dust and germs.
Gaseous exchange happens at the air sacs: oxygen into the blood, carbon dioxide out.
Millions of air sacs give a large surface area.
Inhaled air has more oxygen; exhaled air has more carbon dioxide — never pure!
The circulatory system is the heart, the blood vessels and the blood.
The heart pumps; the blood transports.
Blood carries oxygen from the lungs and digested food from the small intestine to all body
parts.
And when we exercise, the muscles need more oxygen, so we breathe faster and deeper,
and the heart beats faster.
You've got this! Remember: the heart pumps, and the blood transports.
Link the systems together in your answers, and those Section B marks are yours.
Good luck with your revision, and all the best for PSLE!