Welcome back! Today we're revising another key Primary Five topic: The Water Cycle.
We'll cover the three states of water, evaporation and condensation,
how rain is really made, and the exact phrases that score marks in Section B.
Water exists in three states. Solid, as ice, with a fixed shape and volume.
Liquid, as water, with no fixed shape but a fixed volume.
And gas, as water vapour, with no fixed shape or volume.
Water changes from one state to another by gaining or losing heat,
just like we learnt in the Heat topic. Gain heat to melt, evaporate or boil.
Lose heat to freeze or condense.
Here's the biggest trap in this topic: water vapour is invisible!
If you can see it, it is not water vapour.
Steam, mist, fog and clouds are all made of tiny water droplets,
formed when water vapour condenses.
So never write, I can see the water vapour rising from the kettle.
Write: the white steam seen is tiny water droplets,
formed when the hot water vapour condensed in the cooler air.
Concept two: evaporation.
Memorise this sentence: water gains heat from the surroundings, mainly the Sun,
and evaporates to become water vapour.
Evaporation is slow, happens at any temperature, and only at the surface of the water.
And remember, the Sun is the main source of heat that drives the entire water cycle.
Four factors make evaporation faster, and examiners love all of them.
One: higher temperature, so water gains heat at a faster rate.
Two: a larger exposed surface area, so more water is in contact with the air.
Three: moving air, or wind, which carries the water vapour away faster.
And four: drier surrounding air, which can take in more water vapour.
Put them together: wet clothes dry fastest when spread out, on a hot, windy day!
Concept three: condensation.
Memorise this one too: water vapour in the air comes into contact with a cooler surface,
loses heat, and condenses into tiny water droplets.
Condensation happens faster when the surface is cooler.
It's the opposite of evaporation: heat is lost, not gained.
Now let's put it all together: the water cycle.
Water gains heat from the Sun and evaporates. The water vapour rises and cools.
It condenses into clouds.
The droplets combine and fall as rain, which collects in seas and rivers,
and the cycle repeats.
Because water keeps going round and round, Earth has a continuous supply of fresh water.
Let's go stage by stage. Stage one: evaporation.
Water from seas, rivers and lakes gains heat from the Sun and evaporates to become water va
pour.
Stage two: the water vapour rises, and high up in the sky, the surrounding air is cooler.
Stage three: condensation.
The water vapour loses heat to the cooler air and condenses into tiny water droplets.
Millions of these droplets form clouds. Stage four: rain.
The tiny droplets combine to form bigger, heavier droplets.
When they become too heavy to stay up, they fall as rain. And stage five: collection.
Rainwater flows back into drains, rivers, lakes and seas, and the whole cycle repeats.
Trap alert! Clouds do not melt to form rain. Clouds are not solid, so they cannot melt!
Write: the tiny water droplets combine to form bigger, heavier droplets,
which fall as rain. And here's another one: never write, the water disappeared.
Water never just disappears.
Write: the water gained heat and evaporated to become water vapour.
Always say where the water went.
Here's the classic question: why do water droplets form on the outside of a glass of iced w
ater?
The model answer: water vapour in the surrounding air came into contact with the cooler out
er surface of the glass.
The water vapour lost heat to the cold surface and condensed into water droplets.
And remember: the droplets come from the water vapour in the air,
not from the water inside the glass!
Why do wet clothes dry faster when spread out?
Larger exposed surface area, so more water is in contact with the air. On a hot day?
More heat from the Sun, so water gains heat at a faster rate. On a windy day?
Moving air carries the water vapour away at a faster rate.
Whichever factor the question uses,
always end your answer with: so the water evaporates at a faster rate.
A quick bridge back to the Heat topic: boiling versus evaporation.
Boiling is fast; evaporation is slow.
Boiling happens only at the boiling point; evaporation happens at any temperature.
Boiling happens throughout the liquid; evaporation only at the surface.
The water cycle runs on evaporation. The sea never boils!
You can see a mini water cycle inside a sealed container, like a terrarium,
or a plastic bag over a plant. Water gains heat and evaporates.
The vapour touches the cooler lid, loses heat, and condenses into droplets.
The droplets combine, become heavy, and fall back down.
Now the trap: in a sealed container, the total amount of water does not change.
It only changes state and location.
But in an open container, water vapour escapes, so the water level decreases over time.
Answering technique for Section B. Use these keywords: gains heat from the Sun.
Loses heat to the cooler surface. Evaporates to become water vapour.
Condenses into water droplets. Larger exposed surface area. At a faster or slower rate.
And: the droplets combine and become heavier. Then use the formulas.
For evaporation: the water gained heat and evaporated to become water vapour at a faster ra
te, because...
For condensation: the water vapour came into contact with the cooler surface, lost heat,
and condensed into water droplets.
Time to test yourself!
The water level in an open pond decreased on a hot day,
even though no one removed any water. Explain. Pause the video and try. Ready?
Here's the answer: the water in the pond gained heat from the Sun and evaporated to become
water vapour, which escaped into the air. So the water level decreased.
Let's recap.
Water exists as ice, water and water vapour, and changes state by gaining or losing heat.
Water vapour is invisible: steam, mist and clouds are tiny droplets.
Evaporation: water gains heat, mainly from the Sun, and becomes water vapour.
It's faster with more heat, more wind, a larger surface area, and drier air.
Condensation: water vapour loses heat on a cooler surface and forms droplets.
Rain forms when droplets combine and become heavier. Clouds never melt!
And the cycle repeats, giving Earth a continuous supply of fresh water.
You've got this! Remember: gain heat to evaporate, lose heat to condense.
Use the answer formulas and the keywords, and those Section B marks will rain down on you.
Good luck with your revision, and all the best for PSLE!