Welcome! Today we're revising a very important Primary Five topic: Heat and Its Effects.
We'll cover the key concepts, the classic exam traps,
and exactly how to phrase your answers to score full marks.
First, the most important distinction in this whole topic.
Heat is a form of energy, measured in joules.
Temperature is a measure of how hot or cold something is, measured in degrees Celsius,
using a thermometer. They are not the same thing!
Here's the trap.
Never write, the object has more temperature, or, the heat is thirty degrees.
And remember: an object at a higher temperature does not always contain more heat energy.
A cup of boiling water is hotter,
but a warm swimming pool contains far more heat energy overall,
because it is so much bigger.
Now, the golden rule.
Heat always flows from a hotter object or place, to a cooler object or place.
The hotter object loses heat, so its temperature decreases.
The cooler object gains heat, so its temperature increases.
And heat keeps flowing until both objects reach the same temperature.
Trap alert! There is no such thing as cold moving.
Never write, the cold air entered the cup.
Instead, write, heat from the hot water flowed to the cooler surrounding air.
Memorise this answering formula: heat travels from the hotter object to the cooler object.
The hotter object loses heat and its temperature decreases,
while the cooler object gains heat and its temperature increases.
Heat has three effects you must know. One: a change in temperature.
Two: expansion and contraction. And three: a change of state. Let's look at each one.
When matter gains heat, it expands, increasing in size and volume.
When it loses heat, it contracts. This happens to solids, liquids, and gases.
But here's the trap: the mass does not change!
If a question asks about mass after heating,
the answer is always: the mass remains the same.
Expansion explains so many everyday things.
Railway tracks and bridges have gaps,
so the metal can expand on hot days without buckling.
Overhead cables sag on hot days because they expand and become longer.
Running hot water over a tight metal lid makes it expand, so it's easier to open.
And the liquid in a thermometer rises because it gains heat and expands up the tube.
Next, change of state, when heat is gained.
Melting turns a solid into a liquid: ice melts into water at zero degrees Celsius.
Boiling turns a liquid into a gas rapidly, and only at the boiling point,
one hundred degrees for water.
Evaporation also turns a liquid into a gas, but slowly, and at any temperature.
That's why puddles dry up even on cool days.
When heat is lost, the changes go the other way.
Freezing turns a liquid into a solid: water freezes into ice at zero degrees Celsius.
Condensation turns a gas into a liquid: water vapour touches a cold surface, loses heat,
and forms water droplets. So remember: gain heat to melt, boil or evaporate.
Lose heat to freeze or condense.
Here's a classic question: why do water droplets form on a cold drink can?
The model answer: water vapour in the surrounding air came into contact with the cooler out
er surface of the can.
The water vapour lost heat to the cold surface, and condensed into water droplets.
And remember, the droplets come from the air, not from inside the can!
Examiners love comparing boiling and evaporation. Boiling is fast; evaporation is slow.
Boiling happens only at the boiling point; evaporation happens at any temperature.
And boiling happens throughout the liquid, while evaporation happens only at the surface.
Concept four: conductors and insulators.
A good conductor of heat lets heat pass through quickly.
That's metals, like copper, aluminium, iron and steel.
A poor conductor, or insulator, lets heat pass through slowly, like plastic, wood, rubber,
styrofoam, fabric, air, and water. The trap: an insulator never blocks or stops heat.
It only slows it down.
So write: heat enters the box slowly, keeping the drink cold for longer.
Let's see them at work.
A cooking pot's body is metal, so heat passes quickly from the fire to the food.
The handle is plastic or wood, so heat travels slowly to our hand and doesn't burn us.
Wool traps air, so body heat is lost slowly, keeping us warm.
And a styrofoam cooler box lets heat in slowly, so the ice cream melts slowly.
One special point: air is a very poor conductor,
so materials that trap air make excellent insulators.
Now, answering technique for Section B.
Markers look for these keywords: gains or loses heat,
heat flows from one object to another, temperature increases or decreases,
expands or contracts, good or poor conductor of heat, and at a faster or slower rate.
Follow four steps: identify which object is hotter. State the direction heat flows.
State the effect. Then link back to what the question asked.
Time to test yourself! Ali touched a metal spoon and a wooden spoon left in the same room.
The metal spoon felt colder. Are the spoons at different temperatures?
Pause the video and try. Ready? The answer is no! Both spoons are at room temperature.
Metal is a better conductor of heat than wood,
so it conducts heat away from Ali's hand at a faster rate, making it feel colder.
Let's recap. Heat is energy; temperature is the degree of hotness.
Heat flows from hotter to cooler until temperatures are equal.
Gaining heat means temperature rises, things expand, and may melt, boil or evaporate.
Losing heat means temperature falls, things contract, and may freeze or condense.
Expansion changes size, not mass.
Conductors transfer heat quickly, insulators slowly, and they never block heat.
And finally, never write that cold moves. Only heat moves!
You've got this!
Remember the golden rule, practise the answering formula, and use those keywords.
Good luck with your revision, and all the best for PSLE!